-一座塔  -我需要在春天之前完工
-A tower? -I need it completed by spring.
您有没有考虑过 在外族中寻求合作伙伴
Have you considered seeking partners outside the confines of our own race?
跟我说说你国王的提议
Tell me about your King's proposal
我来决定要不要呈报给我父亲
so I can present it to my father.
如果他有所隐瞒 我是能感受到的
I'd sense it if he were hiding something.
或许他感受到了有所隐瞒的人是你
Perhaps he sensed that it was you who was hiding something.
这是什么地方
What is this place?
努门诺尔岛国
The Island Kingdom of Númenor.
我在考虑推迟参加海洋试炼
I was thinking I might defer.
等海洋试炼开始 那艘船启航时 你必须在船上
When the Sea Trial begins and that ship launches, you will be on it.
我不想惹麻烦
I don't want any trouble.
这是南方大地的地图
It is a map of the Southlands.
它不仅提及了一个地点 还讲述了一项计划
It speaks not only of a place, but a plan.
他们将建立自己的领地
To create a realm of their own.
南方大地正处于严重危险之中
Then the Southlands are in grave danger.
如果索隆真的已经卷土重来 那么南方大地只会是个开始
If Sauron has indeed returned, the Southlands are but the beginning.
如果你们这里有谁想活命
If there are any of you here who want to live...
我们明天日出时刻就一起前往精灵塔
...we make for the Elven tower at first light.
把他带给阿达尔
Bring him to Adar.
据说古时候 索隆有很多个名字
Adar! Sauron was said to have many names in days of old.
也许这就是其中一个
Perhaps this is one of them.
你的同胞没有国王 因为你就是国王
Your people have no king, for you are him.
跟我一起去中洲
Come with me to Middle-earth.
你没有军队
You're still short an army.
这些马上就将改变
That is all about to change.
指环王：力量之戒
第一季第四集
本WEB版外挂字幕由  风吹来的那片云  双语合并
在这座王宫 我们每天 都会齐聚一堂 共同规划岛屿的未来
In this court, we gather daily to hammer out our island's future.
但在“祝福新生儿”仪式中
But at the Blessing of the Children,
我们欢聚一堂 共庆新生 他们长大后将见证这座岛屿的未来
we gather to welcome those who will live that future.
孩子就像冲破海面波涛的朝阳 拥有无限的未来
One as boundless as a sunrise over the rolling sea.
你给她取了什么名字
What name have you chosen for her?
艾琳内尔
Alinel.
愿你能够拥有努门诺尔的力量
May Númenor's strength arise in thee.
愿她的智慧指引你的脚步…
Her wisdom guide thy steps...
有时我们的岛屿也需要“活动”一下
Sometimes our island just needs a stretch.
就像你一样
Just like you.
今天真是美好的一天 摄政女王
-It is a perfect day, Queen Regent.
您要先处理什么事情
What business would you begin with?
她把那个精灵传唤到了王宫
She summoned the Elf to court.
就是今早上的事情
Just this morning.
精灵的同伴动手打了四个公会成员 而弥瑞尔却请她喝茶
Elf's mate attacks four guildsmen, and Míriel has her up for tea?
有可能传唤精灵就是为了要惩罚她
Probably she called the Elf in to punish her.
也有可能是向她讨教
-Or to ask her for orders.
精灵在我们的女王耳边扇阴风点鬼火
And while the Elf whispers poison in our Queen's ear,
谁来替我们说话
-who's speaking for us?
国师
Chancellor! Chancellor!
替我向她问好 好吗 你小声点
Send her my regards, will you? Keep your voice down.
您要来一份吗 先生 来一份吧 先生
Would you like one, sir? Come on, sir.
我不知道您在忙很重要的事
I didn't realize you were in the middle of something important.
国师
Chancellor!
治国之道就是要事无巨细
Statecraft is the art of attending to small matters
事必躬亲
as diligently as grand ones.
我以为你现在已经学到这一点了
I should like to think you'd learned that by now.
我一直在想办法学着变聪明点儿
I was only trying to be clever.
野心不大的人才会只顾一味地变聪明
Cleverness is for men of small ambition.
我更希望你能有智慧 儿子
I'd much rather it if you were wise, my son.
说吧 出什么问题了
Now, what seems to be the trouble, hmm?
有人在我们眼皮底下挑事
We may have a bit of a squall on our hands.
精灵的船悍然停在我们的海岸
Elf ships on our shore?
精灵工匠抢走你们的商业贸易
Elf workers taking your trades?
那些工匠不需要睡觉
Workers who don't sleep,
不会疲倦 也不会变老
don't tire, don't age.
不行
No!
要我说 女王要么是瞎
I say, the Queen's either blind
要么就是精灵的舔狗
or an Elf lover.
就跟她父亲一样
-Just like her father.
-精灵的舔狗  -精灵的舔狗
-Elf lover! -Elf lover!
Elf lover!
精灵的舔狗
Elf lover! Elf lover!
如果那个精灵现在就站在这里 她看到的会是什么
And if the Elf were here now, what would she see?
是努门诺尔的铁血男儿
Men of Númenor,
还是一群只会哭闹的孩子
or a gaggle of mewling children?
我们可是伊甸人的儿女
We are sons and daughters of the Edain.
是国王埃尔洛斯塔尔明雅图尔的后代 他曾亲自率军打败魔苟斯
Of Elros Tar-Minyatur, whose host conquered Morgoth himself.
而现在区区一个 坐船逃难的精灵就能威胁到我们吗
But now one Elf, a castaway, could threaten us?
你们所有人 低头看看自己佩戴的公会徽章
Look down, each of you, at the guild crests you bear.
那可是传承自力量强大之手
The heritage of mighty hands.
正是伟大的祖先用双手竖起了海堤
Of men who laid the Sea Wall.
建造了象征我们文明胜利的 阿美尼洛斯
Who raised Armenelos, triumph of our civilization.
但是现在 区区一个精灵就能威胁我们
But now, one Elf could threaten us?
朋友们…
My friends...
相信我
Trust in me.
看看我手上的老茧
For by the calluses on my hands,
我发誓精灵之手 永远无法夺走努门诺尔王国的船舵
I swear that Elven hands will never take Númenor's helm.
努门诺尔王国将一如既往地属于人类
She will remain, as always, a kingdom of Men.
我请大家喝一杯
Drinks all around!
他熟知这座城市里每个人的名字
Isn't a name in this city he doesn't know,
总能说服人群改变想法 几乎所有人都欠他人情
a crowd he can't turn, a favor he isn't owed...
太了不起了
It's impressive.
我本来想说“太让人不爽了”
I was going to say "infuriating."
这酒产自美尼尔塔玛的葡萄园
From vineyards near the Meneltarma.
应该能让你忘记烦恼 反正人们是这么说的
Supposed to make you forget your troubles. Or so they say.
这些甜蜜的烦恼都是我自己争取来的
My troubles have been too hard-won.
你就是那个新来的学徒
You must be the new apprentice.
我叫凯门 你叫…
I'm Kemen. And your name is...
埃雅瑞恩 赶紧交平面图
Hey, E?rien. Plans, now.
你惹恼我了 精灵
You vex me, Elf.
我对你以礼相待
I welcome you as a guest,
你却跑到我们乡下去偷古老的卷轴
and you gallop off to our countryside to steal ancient scrolls
与此同时 你那位来自中洲南方的 同伴还打了我们的公民
whilst your Southlander companion assaults our citizenry.
他的暴脾气可以理解 毕竟他的人民正在死去
He is understandably quick to temper. His people are dying.
“他的人民”
"His people"?
我相信你关在地牢里的那一位 并不是普通的闹事者
I believe the man you hold in your dungeons is no common brawler,
而是流亡在外 下落不明的南方大地王位继承人
but the lost heir in exile to the throne of the Southlands.
那看来埃兰迪尔是一位东夷皇帝
And I suppose Elendil here is a Rh?nic emperor.
其实也就是个小领主
Just a petty lord, actually.
他的人民散落各地 群龙无首
His people are scattered. Leaderless.
但有了你的支持 他们可能会 团结在他的旗帜之下 共同战斗
But with your backing they might unite behind his banner. And fight.
你说的“支持”是什么意思
What do you mean "backing"?
索隆曾经是你们人类的敌人 也是我们精灵的敌人
Sauron was once your people's enemy, as much as mine.
我请求您完成这件未竟之事
I call on you to finish the task left undone.
重建努门诺尔和精灵之间的联盟…
To reforge the alliance between Númenor and Elves...
和我并肩作战 拯救南方大地的人类
And fight with me, to save the men of the Southlands
避免索隆将他们的土地据为己有
before Sauron claims their lands for his own.
在这个王宫之中 我们经常听到许多提案
In this court we hear many proposals.
你的提案是几周来 我听过最令人惊讶、最具野心的
I dare say yours is the most surprising and ambitious I've heard in weeks.
但是 努门诺尔已经 选择了另一条道路
Nevertheless, Númenor has chosen another path.
并非所有人都是如此
Not all Númenor.
那个来自南方大地的人 不管 他是国王还是木匠 都将面临审判
King or carpenter, the Southlander will face judgment.
本次会面结束
This audience is ended.
那我别无选择了 只能要求另一场会面
Then I have little choice, but to ask for another.
我要求与努门诺尔真正的统治者会面
One with Númenor's true ruler.
也就是你的父亲 国王
Your father, the King.
你不应该说起你根本不了解的事情
You should not speak of matters you do not understand,
加拉德瑞尔 菲纳芬之女
Galadriel, daughter of Finarfin.
你应该靠边站
And you should stand aside,
这样我才能 向真正有权答复我的人提出提案
that I might present my proposal to one who holds the authority to answer it.
加拉德瑞尔女士 够了…
Lady Galadriel, that is quite enough.
你凭什么说这番话 精灵
And with what authority do you speak, Elf?
就凭你的人民
That of your people?
还是说你就是个坐船逃难的精灵 想在风暴中抓住救命稻草
Or are you a castaway, grasping for a handhold in a tempest?
我内心就有一股强烈的风暴
There is a tempest in me.
它把我刮到这座岛上一定是有原因的
It swept me to this island for a reason.
而你无法平息这股风暴 摄政王
And it will not be quelled by you, Regent.
我猜猜看
Don't tell me.
是因为在酒馆斗殴进来的
Tavern brawl?
因为发表煽动性言论
Sedition.
你们就快要成功了
You've nearly made it!
再过几天
In a few more days,
我就能很荣幸地 称呼你们所有人为船员了
I'll have the pleasure of calling all of you shipmates.
快拉 学员们 拉
Pull now, cadets! Pull!
伊熙尔杜…
Isildur...
快拉 学员们
Pull now, cadets!
拉
Pull!
绳索
Line!
你们好好解释一下
Explain yourselves.
长官 这肯定搞错了
Sir, no, there must be some sort of mistake.
是我的错 航海官
It was my fault, Sea-master.
是我放手了
I let it slip.
那条升降索 我见过你成功收放不下一百次
I've seen you ease that halyard proper a hundred times.
刚才是故意的
That was deliberate.
你被踢出海上卫队了
You're off the Sea Guard!
你们仨全部淘汰
All three of you!
“西部” “真正的努门诺尔”
"The West"? "The real Númenor"?
又是你哥常挂在嘴边的那些胡话
That garbage your brother used to spew, again!
我还以为航海官只会开除我
I thought the sail-master would only dismiss me.
对不起
I'm sorry.
你对不起
You're sorry?
你对不起  你刚刚毁了我们俩的一生
You're sorry? You just set our whole lives on fire!
夜壶在哪里 我要吐了
Where's that chamber pot? I think I'm gonna be sick.
我去和我爸谈谈
I will speak to my father.
-给你们俩恢复原职 -用不着
Convince him to see that you're both reinstated.
托你的福给踢出来
No. Leave it to you to get kicked out of something
更别说这个机会 本来也不是你自己赢来的
you never earned in the first place.
-维蓝迪尔… -不
-Valandil... -No.
自打我能握住船桨起 我就一直想登上那艘船
Since I was big enough to hold an oar, I wanted on that boat.
我做好了一切准备 拼尽全力去争取 而你又做了什么
I did everything I was supposed to do to earn it. And what did you do?
除了念叨你死去的母亲 你还做过什么?
What have you ever done but brood and blabber about your dead mother.
住手 够了
-Stop it! Stop it! Enough!
又是伊熙尔杜标志性的转身走人
Yeah, same old Isil walking away.
伊熙尔杜 你要去哪
Isil! Where are you going?
是去是留 有什么关系吗
Going, staying, what does it matter?
他才是真正的问题所在 这是无可争辩的事实
The real problem is him. And that's not going anywhere.
马格罗特
Magrot!
阿达尔…
Adar...
无惧赴死
Nampak uglursha.
你的出生地在哪里…
Where were you born,
士兵
soldier?
贝烈瑞安德
Beleriand.
在河口附近
By the mouth of the river?
你是谁
Who are you?
我曾经去过那条河
I went down that river once...
那时我还年轻
When I was young.
我记得…
I remember...
河岸上开满了鼠尾草花
The banks were covered in sage blossoms.
绵延好几英里
Miles of them.
为什么奥克称呼你为父亲
Why do the Orcs call you Father?
你听过很多谎言
You have been told many lies.
有的谎言编得很真
Some run so deep,
现在就连岩石和树根都会相信
even the rocks and roots now believe them.
要揭开谎言…
To untangle it all...
几乎需要创造一个新世界
would all but require the creation of a new world.
但那是只有神才能做到的事
But that is something only the gods can do.
我不是神 起码…
And I am no god. At least...
暂时还不是
Not yet.
你到底是什么东西
What are you?
你去找那些在旧瞭望塔避难的人
Go to the Men who have taken refuge in the old watchtower.
给他们捎个口信
Deliver to them a message.
什么口信
What message?
兵营已经满了 大家尽可能找地方扎营
The barracks are already full. Try and make camp where you can.
-这些人是从哪来的  -罗尔巴德
-Where's this lot from? -Iorbad.
那么从这儿到欧洛朱因 所有村庄的人都到齐了
That makes it every village from here to Orodruin.
剩下的呢
Where's the rest?
只剩下这些了
That is the rest.
我们还得减少口粮配额
We'll have to cut rations again.
你不能减我的配额
You're not cutting my rations.
-是谁给你的决定权  -当然是每个决定来这里
Who gave you the right to decide?
来这座瓦尔德雷格瞭望塔的人 其中也包括你
Everyone who decided to come to this tower, Waldreg. Including you.
那我们吃什么
What will we eat?
-我们会想出办法的 -什么办法
-We'll find a way. -How?
-我不知道 -你能知道才怪了
-I don't know. -Huh. Plain enough to see that.
去瓦尔德雷格的地窖看看怎么样
What about Waldreg's root cellar?
我们派一个小队进镇里去
We send a small party into town.
等白天奥克数量比较少时 悄悄行动 把能拿走的东西迅速拿走
By day, when the Orcs are fewer, grab what we can, quick and quiet.
奥克根本不会知道我们去过
They'll never even know we were there.
你准备忽悠哪些倒霉蛋去干这事
What poor sod will you rope into that?
如果其他人不愿意去 我自己去
I'll do it, if nobody else will.
你不能去
You're not going down there.
我们先再次上山觅食 去召集猎人吧
We'll forage the hills again first. Gather the hunters.
他们去捕什么 几只兔子吗
And what will they hunt? A few rabbits?
那只够我们撑一天
That'll feed us a day.
撑过一天是一天 能多撑一天就应该心存感激
Then it's another day. And let us be grateful for it.
我受够了这样
I'm sick and tired
看着一切支离破碎却无动于衷
of watching everything go to tatters and not doing anything about it.
-我们已经在尽力而为了 -但我没有
-We are doing everything we can. -Well, I'm not!
希奥
Theo. Theo!
你要么帮我 要么就是给我找麻烦
You can either help me or you can make it harder.
我刚才就不应该听你的
I should never have let you talk me into this.
我要回去
I'm heading back.
别这么怂
Don't be such a soft-belly.
走吧
Come on.
罗恩 那边有小酒馆
Rowan, the tavern.
我可不进去
I'm not going in there.
里边可能有更多的食物
-There might be more food.
拜托 那个地方已经荒废了
Come on, this place is deserted.
好吧 那我去
All right. I'll go.
罗恩
Rowan?
童子血
Young blood.
这你是从哪儿弄来的
Where'd you get that?
给我
Give it here.
喂 我找到了
Oi! I found it!
我找到了 是个小男孩  他手上有剑
I found it! It's a boy! He has the hilt!
男孩 他在哪里
A boy? Where is he?
他就躲在这附近
-He's hiding here somewhere.
你 去向父亲大人报告
You! Send word to Lord-father.
其他人 散开搜
Rest of you, fan out.
找不到他 谁也别想睡觉
Nobody sleeps till he's found.
找到你了
Got ya!
精灵和矮人通力合作 真了不起
Elves and Dwarves working together. Remarkable.
都被你言中了
It is everything you said it would be.
怎么了
What?
没什么 只是…
Nothing. Just...
你站在那里 有那么一瞬间 像极了你父亲
For a moment, standing there, you were the very image of your father.
-我都不知道你见过我父亲 -当然了 见过很多次
I wasn't aware you'd ever met him. Of course, many times.
他拥有远眺未来的能力
He had that way of seeing far off.
你知道吗 我记得有一次 他对我说
Do you know, I remember once, he said to me,
“总有一天 我的未来都将掌握在我儿子手中”
one day, my future would be in his son's hands.
他说得很随意 就好像是在说明天要下雨似的
He said it quite casually, as if one might speak of tomorrow's rain.
但我却…
And I've... I've...
我都忘了 直到…直到此时此刻
I'd forgotten that until... Till this moment.
这不是很奇怪吗
Isn't that odd?
陛下 您今天似乎很不安
You seem unsettled today, my lord.
什么事情在困扰您
-What troubles you?
不行 我向自己保证过绝不提起 他毕竟是你朋友
No, I promised myself I wouldn't mention it. He's your friend.
都林
Durin.
他要么是在躲避我 要么是在隐瞒什么
Either he's avoiding me or he's... he's hiding something.
你问过他出工的团队了吗
Did you try asking his work teams?
19个矮人我都问了 他们全都在找借口推辞我
All nineteen of them. They keep putting me off.
让我感觉近乎可疑了
One would almost think it suspicious.
你是在暗示 都林给自己找了个小女朋友吗
Are you suggesting Durin's got himself a wee girlfriend?
-夫人 你是都林的唯一 -我知道
-There is none other than you, milady. -I know.
谁会要他啊
-Who'd have him?
老富婆 亲石头 抛光宝石 把金打磨
Rich crone, kiss the stone Polish your gems and gold
别闹了
-Ow! Stop it!
格尔达 别打你弟弟了
Gerda, stop hitting your brother!
-我们在玩敲门游戏 -好吧 别闹了
We're playing the knocking game. -Well, knock it off.
你去金色阶梯找过了吗
Have you tried the Golden Stairs?
或者三门守卫
Or the Three-door Guard?
我忘了
I'd forgotten.
这些熊孩子把我的脑子都喊糊涂了
These wee'ns are turning my mind to mush.
他今天去石英矿坑采矿去了
He was off to mine Quartz Chasm today.
你知道吗 迪莎 没有什么秘密值得用欺骗来掩饰
You know, Disa, there is no secret worth concealing with deception.
你在我家指着鼻子说矮人不诚实
Calling a Dwarf dishonest in her own home?
这话火药味颇浓啊
That's a recipe for strong gravy.
如果都林在采石英矿
If Durin is mining quartz,
那他为什么不带着他的凿斧
why would he leave without taking his chiseling axe?
而且你为什么 这么早就准备他爱吃的菜
And why would you prepare his favorite meal
他需要两天时间才能下降到那个矿坑
if he's gone to a chasm that takes two full days to descend to?
老富婆 亲石头 抛光宝石…
Rich crone, kiss the stone Polish your gems and gold
格尔达 我警告你
Gerda, I'm warning you!
都林没有带斧头
Durin didn't bring his axe
是因为他开采的石英不需要凿 而是需要撬的
because the quartz he's mining isn't chiseled. It is pried.
我在做鼹鼠尾炖菜
I am making mole-tail stew
是因为赶在他回家之前 做好这道菜还需要花上一些时间
because it needs a wee while to set before he's home.
虽然对于像你这样的外族来说 下降到矿坑可能需要几天时间
And while it may take several days for an outsider, such as you,
但像我丈夫一样的矮人攀登者
Dwarven climbers like my husband
可以在几个小时内就下降到石英矿坑
can make the descent to Quartz Chasm in just a few hours.
你还有什么想问的吗 亲爱的
Was there anything else you wanted to ask about, dearie?
没有了
No.
谢谢
Thank you.
石英矿坑 编得不错
Quartz Chasm. Not bad. Not bad.
我就盼着他信了我 那个精灵可真不容易骗啊
I just hope he believed me. He's not easily taken in, that Elf.
肯定不容易骗
Certainly not.
幸运的是 我未来的女王居然能把精灵忽悠信了
Lucky my future queen could convince a water rat to wear a mink coat.
又多了一个娶了你的好处 幸亏当年没娶马吉德鲁斯特博林
One more reason to count my blessings I married you, not Margid Rustborin.
还有什么其他好处
And what are the other reasons?
回头告诉你
I'll tell you later.
安静 我们最好还是小声点
Hush now. We better keep our pipes down.
我们的旧矿开采进展顺利
We're making good progress in the old mine.
我确保他被护送离开…
I made sure he was escorted out...
镜影湖下面的旧矿场
The old mine below the Mirrormere.
精灵 你迷路了吗
You lost, Elf?
没有 我很清楚自己要去哪
No. I know exactly where I'm going.
日安
-Good day.
老富婆 亲石头 抛光宝石 把金打磨
-Rich crone, kiss the stone. Polish your gems and gold.
我就知道
I knew it!
都林
Durin?
精灵 你是来监视我的吗
-Came to spy on me, Elf? -Hardly.
并不是 这是什么地方
-What is this place?
你真指望我相信你什么都不知道吗
You really expect me to believe you do not know?
这不是他派你来的真正原因吗
That this was not the true reason he sent you here to begin with?
你们想要据为己有
You want it for yourselves.
都林 想要什么
Durin, want what?
我根本不在乎那个洞穴里有什么东西
I care nothing for whatever is in that chamber.
我只在乎你 在乎这份友谊
I do care for you, for this friendship.
而秘密是会阻碍友谊的
And secrets do not become it.
这么大场面是在干什么
What is the meaning of all this? Mm?
你得发誓
I need your oath.
向山起誓
Hand to mountain,
你永远不会将我要告诉你的事情
you'll never breathe so much as a whisper
告诉其他生灵 哪怕是轻声细语也不行
of what I'm about to tell you to another living soul.
矮人的记仇能力比精灵的记忆力还强
Dwarven anger outlives even Elven memory.
如果你违背誓言
Break your promise,
这块石头的力量 必将令你和你的亲人陷入悲伤
and the power of this stone will doom you and your kin to sorrow,
直至你们活在中洲的最后一天
to your last day on this Middle-earth.
你敢这样发誓吗 埃尔隆德
Do you swear it, Elrond?
我以我父亲 水手埃雅仁迪尔的名义起誓
I swear on the memory of my father, E?rendil the Mariner.
你在这里告诉我的任何事情 都将止于我
Anything you tell me here will end in my ears alone.
迪莎在一次例行的金矿搜寻中 发现了这个
Disa detected it during a routine gold-seaming.
这是一种新矿石
A new ore.
比丝轻 比铁硬
Lighter than silk, harder than iron,
用作武器 它比我们最引以为豪的兵刃还要锋利
as weaponry, it would best our proudest blades.
作为实物 它可能比黄金还珍贵
As specie, it might be dearer than gold.
它反射光线的方式很奇特
It is strange how it catches the light.
好像矿石内部就在发光
Almost seems lit from within.
我跟你说 这可能是我们矮人新时代的开始
I tell you, this could be the beginning of a new era for our people.
力量、繁荣…
Strength, prosperity...
那为什么要藏着掖着
Then why all the secrecy?
为什么不庆祝一番呢
Why not celebrate this?
这种矿的开采非常危险
It's perilous to mine.
我父亲打着谨慎的名义
My father has restricted our every efforts
处处限制我们开采
in the name of caution.
我能看看吗
May I?
你怎么称呼这种神奇的矿石
What do you call this miracle ore?
在我们的语言里 叫“灰色的闪光”
In our tongue, "gray glitter."
用你们的话 可能叫什么“米银”
In yours, something like mith-raud.
不不不 是秘银
No, no. It would be... mithril.
所以你远道而来 就只为了埃瑞吉安
So you really did come all this way just for Eregion?
我来这里是因为 20年不见老朋友一面 太久了
I came because 20 years is far too long to stay away.
连我这个精灵都觉得久
Even for an Elf.
收下吧
Keep it.
象征着我们的友谊
Token of our friendship.
很好
Very well.
都林 不要
No! Durin! Durin! Durin, no!
下面有四个矮人
There's four Dwarves down there!
都林
Durin!
埃雅瑞恩 扫地 洗高脚杯
E?rien, floors and goblets.
实在对不起
I'm so sorry.
没关系 说真的 没事的
It's all right. It's all right. It's... It's... It's all right, honestly.
我还以为你只擅长制图呢
And here I thought your talents ended at draftsmanship.
擦擦洗洗会让人更加灵巧
Scrubbing is good for dexterity.
会长是这么说的
Or so the guild master says.
你看这样如何  我擦地板 你洗高脚杯
So, how about this? I'll do the floors, you do the goblets.
谁擦得慢 晚餐钱就由谁来付
And the last one to finish pays for dinner.
我不和不认识的年轻男士约会
I'm not in the habit of going off with strange young men.
很明智 如果我看到 哪个男士举止怪异 立马告诉你
Very wise. If I see any, you'll be the first to know.
尽管我很佩服你 每次遇到困难都会冲锋陷阵
As much as I admire your habit of charging at every obstacle in your path,
就像一匹全速奔跑的小马…
like a colt in full gallop...
但你有没有想过 你不是在和食人妖或奥克作斗争
Has it ever occurred to you that you're not battling trolls or Orcs,
而是和人类
but Men?
你是真的要给我兵法方面的建议吗
Are you really about to advise me in the art of war?
不是 我…
No. No, I...
我可不敢 但是…
I wouldn't dare. But then...
女王的王宫 和你平日的战场并不相同 没错吧
The queen's court isn't exactly your usual battlefield, is it?
接着说
Go on.
在这种情况下 依我看
In an instance like this, it seems to me
你最好要弄清楚对手最害怕的是什么
that you'd do well to identify what it is that your opponent most fears.
-然后利用这一点  -不是
-And exploit it? -No.
是要给他们一种掌控这种恐惧的方法
Give them a means of mastering it.
这样你就可以掌控对手
So that you can master them.
所以按照你的标准 我在这个牢房
So by your standards, I'm in this cell,
是因为我还没有找出 女王最害怕什么
because I've yet to identify what the queen most fears?
你只达到了低标准 但没错
My very low standards. Yes.
你只见了女王一小会儿 看来你已经确定了她最害怕什么
And I suppose you did, having met her for all of a few moments?
会面期间 你索要了船只 侮辱了她的人民、违抗了她的命令
During which you managed to demand a ship, insult her people, defy her orders,
但这些都没有让她情绪起伏
none of which quickened her pulse.
现在 突然间 她把你扔进了牢房
Now, all of a sudden, she throws you in a cell.
为什么
Why?
我请求她为你的人民而战
I asked her to fight for your people.
但这不是引起她愤怒的原因吧
But that wasn't what provoked her anger, was it?
我要求和她父亲会面
I demanded to speak with her father.
多年来 没有人见过的 塔中的国王
The king in the tower, whom no one has seen in years.
现在你知道停止奔跑 给自己 一点时间思考 会发生什么了吧
See what happens when you stop galloping and you give yourself a moment to think?
别再把我比作一匹马了
Cease comparing me to a horse.
作为交换 那你别再说服我离开这座岛了
Cease trying to convince me to leave this island an you have a deal.
请注意 精灵
Salutations, Elf.
摄政女王做出了决定
The Queen Regent has rendered her decision.
今晚 你将在武装护送下 被运回精灵的领地
You are to be shipped back to the Elves under armed escort. Tonight.
向前一步
Step forward.
-我不建议你这样做 -我不能让她就这样离开
-I wouldn't advise that. -I can't very well let her leave.
你如果知道她要去哪里的话 你肯定会放她走
-You could. If you knew exactly where she was going.
你来这上面干什么
What are you doing up here?
我刚跟人约会吃饭去了
I had a dinner.
跟谁
Who is he?
你的制服呢
Where's your uniform?
你是辞职不当学员了吗
Resigned from the cadets, did you?
不是 比这更糟糕
No, worse.
你被开除了
You got dismissed?
我害得我们几个都被开除了
Got us all dismissed.
伊熙尔…
Isil...
好吧 你赢了 现在你可以去西部了
Well, you've won. Now you can go west.
我毁了朋友们的生活
I just ruined my friends' lives,
羞辱了家门
shamed our family name.
我不配去西部
I don't deserve to go west.
再说了 父亲不会让我带走贝雷克的
-Plus, Father won't let me take Berek.
是那个精灵 她逃出来了
It's the Elf! She's escaped.
仔细搜查每一个小巷
Search every alley.
抱歉 陛下 打扰了 但是我…
Apologies, Your Majesty, for the intrusion. But I...
他已经没法再回应了
He no longer answers to that.
你怎么知道我会来这里
How did you know I would come here?
外面有一支驻军等着护送你上船
A garrison of troops awaits outside to escort you to your ship.
你放聪明点 自己主动离开
You would be wise to go willingly.
弥瑞尔
Míriel.
我…
I... I...
没事的 父亲 我在呢
-It's all right, Father. I'm here.
请原谅我
Forgive me.
我不知道是这个情况
I did not know.
没几个人知道 他身体恶化到了这种地步
Few know the full extent of his decline.
我希望继续瞒着所有人
I should like to keep it that way.
那我们俩之间就开诚布公吧
Then it is time for truth between us.
你父亲之前忠于精灵
Your father was loyal to the Elvish ways.
你为什么不愿意
Why are you not?
告诉我
Tell me.
拜托了
Please.
我父亲以前对他的信念总是很克制
My father was always restrained in his beliefs.
但在他加冕之后 情况发生了变化
But after his coronation, something changed.
他开始变得很强硬
He became strident,
宣称我们激怒了维拉
proclaiming that we'd provoked the anger of the Valar,
宣称我们必须悔改 回归往日的道路
and must repent, and return to the old ways.
有民众对此感到不安
There was unease.
而当我父亲宣布 计划与精灵再续友好关系时…
And when he announced plans to renew relations with the Elves...
民众造反了
The people rebelled.
损失惨重
Much was lost.
我被选中接替他的统治
I was chosen to rule in his stead,
承诺要平息动乱
with a promise to quell the storm.
但我继位的第一个晚上 等努门诺尔人都睡着了
But that first night, as all Númenor slept,
父亲把我带到了这里
he brought me here.
帕蓝提尔
Palantír.
曾经有七颗真知晶石
Seven Seeing Stones there once were.
其他六颗丢的丢 藏的藏
The other six either lost or hidden.
这一颗传给了我父亲
This one was passed to my father.
它有一个秘密
And with it, a secret.
把你的手放在上面
Place your hand upon it.
-我得警告你… -我以前触摸过帕蓝提尔
-I must warn you... -I have touched palantíri before.
但你没有碰过这一颗
But you have not touched this one.
你刚才看到的是努门诺尔的未来
It is Númenor's future you saw.
帕蓝提尔能呈现出很多异象
Palantíri show many visions.
但有些异象永远不会发生
Some that will never come to pass.
它已经发生了
It has already come to pass.
自打你来到这里 这个异象就开始了
The vision begins with your arrival.
你认为我会导致努门诺尔的覆灭吗
And you believe I will bring about Númenor's downfall?
只有努门诺尔才能让自己覆灭
Only Númenor can bring about her downfall.
在一个恩德圆满的日子 维拉将这座岛屿赐予了我们
The Valar gifted us this isle in a day of virtue.
倘若我们调头走向黑暗 那他们大可把这座岛屿收回
They can take it away should we turn to the paths of darkness.
你所说的恩德 就是你祖先对精灵的忠诚
The virtue you speak of was your ancestors' loyalty to the Elves.
我父亲对此深信不疑
My father believed that.
而他带领的路差点让我们毁于一旦
His path nearly destroyed us.
这就是为什么 明天我要宣布你已经走了
That is why, tomorrow, I will announce that you are gone.
同时宣布这场危机结束
And this crisis ended.
如果对中洲 正在崛起的邪恶势力放任不管
If the evil rising in Middle-earth is left unchecked,
那它必然扩散 毁灭我们所有人
it will spread and take us all.
刻意避免这场战争 可能恰恰就是导致你们覆灭的原因
Avoiding this war may be the very thing that brings about your downfall.
我不会质疑诸神 这就是我最后的决定
I will not second-guess the gods. My decision is final.
是出于恐惧而做的决定吧
A decision based in fear.
我知道作为唯一知情的人 是什么样的感受
I know what it is to be the only one,
唯有自己能看到
the only one who sees,
唯有自己才知情
the only one who knows.
也许我们俩 都不必再独自承担这个负担了
Perhaps neither of us have to bear that burden alone any longer.
我求你了 弥瑞尔 不要选择恐惧的那条道路
I beg of you, Míriel, choose not the path of fear,
要选择充满信念的那条路
but that of faith.
和我站在一起
Stand with me.
让努门诺尔再次与精灵并肩作战
Let Númenor fight alongside the Elves once more.
内心可以遵从信念 加拉德瑞尔
Faith may bind one heart, Galadriel.
但要让一个王国只依靠信念 实在是有点靠不住
But it is too fine a thread from which to hang a kingdom.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
树林都是光秃秃的 动物也都四散逃走了
Woods are all bare. Animals are all fled.
看来你的孩子比我们原以为的更聪明
Seems your boy had more sense than we allowed.
门口有人
-There's someone at the gates!
退后
Stand back.
-别挡路 退后  -让这小伙子过去
-Move out of the way. Stand back! -Let the lad through!
有很多吃的 慢点
There's plenty. Slow down!
罗恩 希奥在哪
Rowan! Where's Theo?
他刚才说会紧跟着我
He said he'd be right behind me.
-好饿  -别推了
-I'm so hungry! -Stop pushing!
她推我
She pushed me!
我们把每个角落都检查过了 他没回来
We've turned over every stone. He ain't back here.
走吧
-Come on.
他在哪里
Where is he?
他不在这里
He's not here!
我们走
Let's go.
仔细搜查 不留死角
Leave no stone unturned.
要是找不到他 老大会活剥了我们的皮
Boss will skin us alive if we don't find him.
是老大最先把他弄丢的啊
Boss is the one who lost him in the first place.
我闻到他的气味了…
Izm?mbogh...
快过来
Come on!
快搜
Kishdibatoth! Kishdibatoth.
Kishdibatoth.
把他找出来
Find him!
不在这里
Nothin' here.
在那边 看
-Over there! Look!
小鲜肉 你急着要跑去哪儿啊
Going somewhere, young blood, are we?
那把剑在哪里
Where is it?
不要
No!
你从哪儿弄到的
Where have you got it?
砍掉你一只手臂 看你开不开口
Maybe losing your arm will loosen your lips.
动作快点 小伙子
-Swiftly, lad. -Over there! Get him!
他们来了
They are coming.
继续跑
Keep going.
快跑
Run!
妈妈
Mother?
布隆温
Bronwyn.
快跑 去空地
Run! Get to the clearing!
刚才这是干什么
What was that?
是在恳求岩石
It was a plea to the rocks
请它保佑矿工还有呼吸 能够安全逃生
to release the bodies of the miners with breath still inside them.
我一直在想 要不是你去矿井找他
I cannot stop thinking that if you'd not gone down there,
都林很有可能会在那个竖井里…
Durin might have been in that shaft when it...
对不起
I'm sorry.
对不起 我骗了你
I'm sorry I lied to you.
你不告诉我也是为了都林好 我们只要记住这个就可以了
You were faithful to my friend. -That is all we need remember.
他们刚把最后一名矿工拖了出来
They just pulled out the last one.
活着 他们都活着
-Alive. All of them alive.
你父亲肯定松了一口气
Your father must be so relieved.
他把矿井关停了
He shut it down.
整条矿脉都要被封死了
The whole vein is to be sealed off.
-整条矿脉  -一整条
-The whole vein? -All of it.
给他点时间嘛
Give him time.
脾气再大 气也总会消的
Even the hottest coals eventually cool.
是啊 但有时候 我倒是希望他一直在气头上
Yeah, but sometimes I wish they wouldn't.
有时候我真希望 能告诉父亲我对他的真实看法
Sometimes I wish I could tell him exactly what I think of him,
然后再也不和那个糟老头子说话了
and never trade words with the old goat again!
我父亲曾经独自航行到维林诺
My father single-handedly sailed to Valinor,
说服维拉加入战争 并成功消灭魔苟斯
and convinced the Valar to join the war and vanquish Morgoth.
他的事迹如此伟大
So great were his deeds
以至于维拉 把他带到了这个世界的边界之外…
that the Valar lifted him beyond the bounds of this world...
永远带着暮色之星划过天空
To forever carry the Evening Star across the sky.
这么多年来 每到深夜 我都会抬头看看它…
For many years, at day's end, I would look up at it...
想知道如果他在看着我 他会怎么想
Wondering what might he think if he were watching me.
他会为我在他的传承之上 取得的成就而感到骄傲吗
Would he be proud of what I've accomplished with his legacy?
还是会因为我未能达到 他的种种期望而对我感到失望
Or disappointed by the countless ways I'd failed to live up to it?
但后来有一天晚上 我突然想到
But then, one night, it struck me
只要能听到他的评价 无论好坏 我都能心满意足
that I would be only too happy to hear any judgment,
我只求获得再次与父亲说话的机会
so long as it granted me the opportunity
哪怕只有一次也好
to have but one more conversation with my father.
不要浪费你和父亲所剩不多的时间
Do not waste what time you have left with yours.
埃尔隆德 我期待你能解答一些问题
Elrond, I was hopeful you might be able to settle something.
你和我老公是怎么认识的
How is it that you and my husband met?
我告诉过你 我把他从山岭食人妖手中救了出来
I told you, I saved him from a hill-troll.
-是两个山岭食人妖哦 -两个 对 我知道
-Two of 'em. -Two of 'em. Yes, I know.
我是在问埃尔隆德
I was asking Elrond.
那恐怕我别无选择 只能纠正一下你丈夫的描述
Then I fear I have no choice but to amend your husband's account.
当时有三个山岭食人妖 而且是我救的他
There were three trolls. And it was I who saved him.
你也不照照镜子看看自己长什么样子
You wouldn't remember your face if you were gazing in a mirror.
当时我在森林里遇见他
When I came upon him in the forest,
他正在躲避山岭食人妖的槌击
he was in the midst of dodging their mallet blows.
他就在那里嚎啕大哭什么的
-Wailing and screaming and such.
我那是战场的呐喊
-It was a battle cry.
他的喊叫声非常尖锐 我当时还以为是个小孩 我拿着弓…
The screams were so high-pitched, I thought it was a child. So I took up my bow...
-是一把剑 -是一把弓
-Uh, it was a sword. -It was a bow.
-不 是一把剑  -不管怎么样…
-Nah! It was a sword! -Regardless...
原谅我 父亲
Forgive me, Father.
我太过骄傲、固执 我错了
I was proud and stubborn and I was wrong.
你就不能看我一眼吗
Can you not even look at me?
我们矮人相信…
Our people believe...
当新的矮人国王加冕时
That when a new Dwarf-king is crowned,
所有祖先的声音都会汇集在他心头
the voices of all his forebearers flow into him,
与他分享前辈们的经验
sharing with him their counsel
以及智慧
and wisdom.
甚至还有错误
-Even their mistakes.
但你…
But you...
你不必等到那一天 就能听到我的声音
You need not wait for that day to hear my voice.
因为 儿子 我永远和你在一起
For, ever am I with you, my son.
即便我非常愤怒
Even in anger.
有的时候 我基本上一直在发怒
Sometimes, in anger most of all.
你没什么需要我原谅的
There is nothing to forgive.
埃尔隆德邀请我明天和他一起去林顿
Elrond has invited me to go with him to Lindon tomorrow.
我应该接受吗
Shall I accept?
埃尔隆德保证 吉尔加拉德派他来这里并没有恶意
Elrond has been very convincing in his assurances
埃尔隆德的话让人非常信服
that Gil-galad bore no ill intent when he sent him here.
是的 的确是
Aye. He has.
但直觉是一种强有力的辅助
But intuition's a powerful tonic.
你的直觉如何
What does yours tell you?
感觉事有蹊跷
There is something more at work.
好样的 儿子
Good, my son.
很好
Good.
去林顿吧
Go to Lindon.
看看是怎么回事
Find out what.
谢谢你
Thank you.
怎么了 出什么事了
What is it? What's wrong?
敌人的指挥官让我带回来一条口信
I have a message. From the one who commands our enemy.
你的人民要想保全性命 必须放弃这些土地的所有权…
That your people may live if you forsake all claim to these lands...
并向他宣誓效忠
And swear fealty to him.
如果我们拒绝呢
And if we refuse?
那他就会来欧斯提力斯
He's coming for Ostirith.
来吧
-Come on.
要我说 你的所做作为 配得上喝一口好酒作为奖赏
If you ask me, you deserve a nip of mash after what you done.
给 拿着吧
Go on, take it.
就像你从我谷仓里 拿走了那把剑一样
Just like you took that hilt from me barn.
我不知道你说什么...
Uh... I don't know what...
别装了 小伙子
Come off it, lad.
你知道我说的是什么
You know of what I speak.
你知道这是什么吗 这并不是剑
Do you know what it is? It is no sword.
而是一种力量
It is a power.
由他的主人亲手为我们的祖先打造
Fashioned for our ancestors by his master's own hand.
一个漂亮的仆人
A beautiful servant.
他曾经不知所踪 但终将归来
He who was lost, but shall return.
小伙子 你听说过他吗
Have you heard of him, lad?
你听说过索隆吗
Have you heard of Sauron?
你肯定在天上看到过
You must have seen it in the skies.
几周前
A few weeks back now.
星陨
The starfall.
这意味着他的时间快到了
It means his time is near.
小伙子 这需要你和我共同做好准备
And it is to you and me, lad, to be ready.
准备好什么
Ready for what?
安静点 小伙子
Hush now, lad.
你保存好体力
You save your strength.
接下来要发生的事
You'll need it.
会非常消耗体力的
For what's coming.
父亲大人
Lord-father...
我们找到了
We found it.
在那座塔里
It's in the tower.
安心去吧
Go in peace.
你的人民会感到宽慰
Your people will be relieved.
他们很快就会聚集在王宫里
They will be gathering soon in the court,
聚集在广场上 聆听你的宣告
and in the plaza, to hear your announcement.
那我们就别让他们久等了
Then we ought not to keep them.
忠贞派相信 白树的花瓣落下
The faithful believe that when the petals of the White Tree fall
是重要的预兆…
it is no idle thing,
但是维拉的眼泪
but the very tears of the Valar themselves,
鲜活地提醒着我们 他们时刻紧盯我们 审判我们
a living reminder that their eyes and their judgment are ever upon us.
现在 人类命运迎来了 一个决定性的时刻
There is a fateful hour in the destinies of men.
一个审判的时刻
An hour of judgment
在这之中 我们所有人、每个人
in which each of us, every one,
都必须决定自己将要成为谁
must decide who we shall be.
我们的心会像 小岛周围的石像一样铁石心肠
Are our hearts become as the statues that surround our isle?
还是会同石像雕刻的 英雄一般充满满腔热忱
Or do they yet beat with the blood of the heroes that carved them?
我们的勇气 是否只存在于父辈的坟墓之中
Is our valor confined to the graves of our slumbering fathers?
还是说就在这里
Or is it here,
就在我们众人之中…
amongst us even now...
等待随着太阳升起而迸发
Waiting to burst forth as the rising Sun?
我不会让你们去面对 连我自己都不敢直面的危险
I would neither command, nor invite you to any danger I myself would not face.
所以 我决定亲自护送精灵返回中洲
And so, I've decided to personally escort the Elf back to Middle-earth.
援助被围困在南方大地的凡人同胞
To aid our mortal brethren who are now besieged in the Southlands.
女王已经明确表明意图
Your queen has laid bare her intent.
我们的船队将在十天后启程
Our ships will depart in ten days.
远征军将由努门诺尔全境
The expeditionary force will be made up of brave sons and daughters
勇敢的儿女组成
from across fair Númenor.
有谁愿意真心实意 保护我们的摄政女王
Who is willing to commit themselves to our Queen Regent's protection?
请向前一步让大家看到
Step forward and make yourself known.
我愿意出征
I will serve.
I will serve!
我愿意出征
字幕翻译： 腐哥
创意监督 罗婷婷